Guide to the Joyce Gilbert papers, 1975-2018 MS 805
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Joyce Gilbert papers
1975-2018
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Gilbert, Joyce Kramer
MS 805
.5 Linear Feet 1 box
One box containing certificates, correspondence, a travel journal, photographs, a magazine article, event materials, and a Soviet Jewry nameplate documents Joyce Gilbert's activities in the Houston Jewish community and her work to assist Russian Jewry from 1975 to 2018.
Biographical / Historical
Joyce Kramer Gilbert was born and grew up in New York City. She graduated from The High School of Music and Art and Beaver College (Arcadia University) with a degree in Early Childhood Education. She married Robert David Gilbert in 1957, and they and their three children moved to Houston in 1967.
She began her career with the Jewish Community Center in 1968 as a Nursery School teacher and subsequently was the Director of Children and Youth, Day Camp Director, Outreach Director and the Director of Early Childhood. In 1979 she left the JCC and worked as an Epidemiology Field Worker for a number of years. In 1981, she started her collaboration with the artist Judy Chicago and worked with her on The Birth Project, the Holocaust Project and Resolutions as well as individual pieces. She sat on the board of Through the Flower, the non-profit that supports Judy Chicago's work for approximately 15 years. She continues to design and execute needlework projects, mostly of Judaic subjects. In 1984 she traveled to the then Soviet Union to bring aid to the refusenik community through the auspices of the Union of Councils for Soviet Jews. She directed Houston Action for Soviet Jews and served as a Vice President of the Union of Councils for Soviet Jews. In Houston Joyce has served on the Boards of the Jewish Federation of Greater Houston, the American Jewish Committee from which she received the Susman Award in 2002, and Congregation Brith Shalom for which she was President from 1993-1995. In 2005 Joyce was Chair of the Book and Arts Fair of the ERJCC and continues to be active on committees there.
Scope and Contents
One box containing certificates, correspondence, a travel journal, photographs, a magazine article, event materials, and a Soviet Jewry nameplate documents Joyce Gilbert's activities in the Houston Jewish community and her work to assist Russian Jewry from 1975 to 2018. Of particular interest is Gilbert's travel journal in which she recorded her activities during two trips to the Soviet Union.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in seven series as follows:
Series I: Certificates; Series II: Event Materials; Series III: Memorabilia; Series IV: Personal papers; Series V: Photographs; Series VI: Publications; Series VII: Speeches
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was donated by Joyce Gilbert in October, November, and December of 2018.
Separated Materials
Cookbooks: The ORT Way (1975) and The Passover Plate (1980) were removed, cataloged separately, and are available at the Woodson Research Center. The ORT Way - TX724 .C555 1975 The Passover Plate - TX724 .P377 1981
Index Terms
Document Types
certificates; personal correspondence; programs (documents); books; speeches; photographs; publications
Subjects (Corporations)
Congregation Brith Shalom. (Bellaire, Tex)
- Series I: Certificates, 1980-1984
  - 4th Annual Walk for Israel, 1980-04-20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National Council for Jewish Women, 1980-10-10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificate of Bat Mitzvah, 1984-12-08 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Event Materials, 2002-2007
  - Helene Susman Woman of Prominence Award, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ad book vendors, 2004; 2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - JCC Book Fair program, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brith Shalom Follies, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brith Shalom Past Presidents Celebration invitation, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series III: Memorabilia, n.d.
  - Houston Action for Soviet Jewry nameplate, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Personal Papers, 1996-1999
  - "Thank you" letters, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Journal of Russian travels, October 1984; October 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series V: Photographs, 1974-1984
  - Congregation Brith Shalom confirmation class group photos (3), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Adult Bat Mitzvah, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Joyce and her husband Robert filling in a letter on new Torah scroll, Congregation Brith Shalom (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series VI: Publications, 1975-2018
  - Congregation Brith Shalom Family Pictorial Directory, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Jewish Herald Voice magazine, "Needlepoint 'Tree of Life' Roots Congregation to Torah", 2018 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series VII: Speeches, 2010
  - d'var Torah at Congregation Brith Shalom, 2010-04-17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series VIII: Oral Histories, 2018
  - Joyce Gilbert oral history interview and transcript, 2018-11-16